Simon Fraser University Childcare Society fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Simon Fraser University Childcare Society fonds
1966 - 1999
F-149
Q106643033
58 cm of textual records 28 photographs 6 sound recordings
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION The 6 audio recordings include 12 audio cassettes (originals and copies). GENERAL NOTE Photographs are located in series 4; sound recordings are located in series 5.
Simon Fraser University Childcare Society
The SFU Childcare Society presently operates eleven programs that are collectively known as the Children's Centre. The Children's Centre is an independent, legally incorporated non-profit society with registered charitable organization status. The Children's Centre provides full and part time care to approximately 240 children, ranging in age from 3 months to 12 years. Each program has its own physical space and is often referred to as a centre. A Board of Directors is composed of parent representatives, university representatives, childcare staff representatives and community representatives. The Executive Director is an ex-officio, non-voting member of the Board, hired through the University (with direction from the Society Board) to be the Coordinator for the Society and to act as a liaison between the Society and the University.
Daycare began at SFU in 1968 when a group of parents established the Simon Fraser Co-operative Family in a student lounge. By 1973, the Family Co-op had grown into the SFU Day Care Society with three units in different locations. By 1976, there were five licensed daycare centres all incorporated under the Burnaby Mountain Day Care Society.
In 1976 the University provided 1.2 million dollars to fund construction of a childcare complex, the first of its kind in Canada. The University also supported the appointment of a full-time director, Emily Campbell. For funding purposes, the Burnaby Mountain Day Care Society separated into five non-profit societies, which could each apply for grants. The five societies and their nine centres formed a loose federation, The Burnaby Association of University Child Care Societies, to set overall policy, coordinate activities, and exchange information. Centres remained autonomous in financing, staffing, and style of care.
In 1981 it became evident that current levels of University funding were in jeopardy. A Task Force was struck by the University to investigate the current organization of childcare on campus. Following recommendations of that Task Force, the five individual daycare societies were reorganized in 1982 into a single non-profit society, The SFU Childcare Society, which continues today.
The SFU Childcare Society is funded primarily through parent user fees and Board fund raising efforts. These monies are used for staff salaries and benefits, program related expenses, equipment purchase and upkeep, playgrounds, administrative costs and utilities.
A Licensing Agreement with the University provides for repairs and maintenance service for all the major building structures, comprehensive insurance, and the salary and benefits for the Executive Director and secretarial positions.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of the organization.
The fonds of the SFU Childcare Society consists of records made or received in the course of administering the Society and its predecessor bodies and providing facilities, personnel and funding for childcare programs. The bulk of the material ranges from 1968 to the early 1990s. Activities documented include meetings of the various societies and centres established to provide childcare services; obtaining license agreements with the University; securing collective agreements with staff; planning for child care services; construction of buildings; correspondence and liaison with government officials and university administrators; and providing information to parents and staff.
The records were originally selected for retention and arranged by the staff of the SFU Childcare Centre from a larger quantity of materials stored at the Centre. The Archivist completed the arrangement of the material to reflect the various societies which provided childcare over the years as well as the activities and functions that generated the records. Within files, documents are generally arranged chronologically.
Davidson, Sheila; Coates, Penny; Branscombe, Joyce E.; Campbell, Emily A.; Sound recordings; Photographic materials; Textual records; Children and youth; Family and personal life; Women; Health and social services
The records were donated to the Archives by the SFU Childcare Society in 1997.
All accessions have been processed as of September 2002. Further accruals are expected. According to the Agreement to Transfer signed by the Simon Fraser University Childcare Society and the Archives, the Society will donate its inactive records to the Archives once every five years.
For other material relating to the SFU Daycare Society, see the Simon Fraser Student Society fonds (F-74), the Student Services fonds (F-107), the records of the Vice-President, University Services (F-207), and the SFU Childcare Society collection (Mary Wilson collector) (F-229).
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
Access to analog sound recordings is restricted due to the fragility of the medium (audio cassettes); consult the reference archivist for more information about accessing these recordings.
File list is available. More detailed histories of the SFU Childcare Society, "The History of Day Care on Campus at Simon Fraser University," Researched and edited by Diane MacDonald, 1979 and "Celebrating 30 Years of Caring," by SFU Childcare, Society, 1968-1998 are available in the hard copy version of the finding aid maintained in the Archives Reading Room.
- Organization records, 1968 - 1998; F-149-1; 34 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the structure and governance of the SFU Childcare Centre and its constituent bodies over time.
  - General administration and history files, 1968 - 1998; F-149-1-1; 22 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records relating to the evolution of the various umbrella societies responsible for childcare at SFU. Includes reports by various committees and task forces about the future of childcare at the University, a 1970 childcare survey, files relating to the construction of the Childcare Centre in 1976, and one file related to general funding issues. Records consist of minutes, constitutions, license agreements with the University, membership agreements, collective agreements, job descriptions, and financial statements.
    - Early development, 1968 - 1998; F-149-1-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 149-1)
      Textual records
      Open
    - Daycare survey, 1970; F-149-1-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 149-1)
      Restricted in whole
    - SFU Day Care Society, 1973; F-149-1-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 149-1)
    - Burnaby Mountain Day Care Society, 1973 - 1974; F-149-1-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 149-1)
      Restricted in part
    - SFU Day Care Council, 1974 - 1976; F-149-1-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 149-1)
    - Burnaby Association of University Child Care Societies 1/2, vol. 1, 1976 - 1981; F-149-1-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 149-1)
    - Burnaby Association of University Child Care Societies 2/2, vol. 2, 1976 - 1981; F-149-1-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 149-1)
    - SFU Childcare Society 1/2, vol. 1, 1978 - 1992; F-149-1-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 149-1)
    - SFU Childcare Society 2/2, vol. 2, 1978 - 1992; F-149-1-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 149-1)
    - Reports, 1981 - 1990; F-149-1-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 149-2)
    - Funding, 1977 - 1989; F-149-1-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 149-2)
    - Advisory Committee on Daycare Building, 1975 - 1977; F-149-1-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 149-2)
    - New building 1/2, 1975 - 1977; F-149-1-1-0-13 (Archival box - standard 149-2)
    - New building 2/2, 1975 - 1977; F-149-1-1-0-14 (Archival box - standard 149-2)
    - Emily Campbell, 1984; F-149-1-1-0-15 (Archival box - standard 149-2)
  - Individual Childcare Centre files, 1974 - 1984; F-149-1-2; 12 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records relating to the development, organization, and administration of the various programs (centres) which were established over the years to provide childcare at SFU. Records consists of minutes, constitutions, license agreements with the University, membership agreements, collective agreements, job descriptions, and financial statements.
    - Alligator Pie 1/2, vol. 1, 1978 - 1982; F-149-1-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 149-2)
    - Alligator Pie 2/2, vol. 2, 1978 - 1982; F-149-1-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 149-2)
    - Building 3 Child Care Society, 1976 - 1982; F-149-1-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 149-3)
    - Crackers Day Care Society, 1980 - 1981; F-149-1-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 149-3)
    - Kahpoo Infant Care Society, 1975 - 1983; F-149-1-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 149-3)
    - Kindergarten Kids Day Care Society, 1979 - 1981; F-149-1-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 149-3)
    - Les Petits unit, 1984; F-149-1-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 149-3)
    - Los Ninos Day Care Society, 1975 - 1976; F-149-1-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 149-3)
    - Nanitsh Day Care Society, 1974 - 1982; F-149-1-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 149-3)
    - Pink Day Care Society, 1975 - 1978; F-149-1-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 149-3)
    - Snake Hill Day Care Society, 1974 - 1978; F-149-1-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 149-3)
- Correspondence, 1966 - 1987; F-149-2; 3 cm of textual records
  Series consists of correspondence between the various SFU childcare societies and provincial, federal and municipal governments; university administrative officials; and the University president and Board of Governors.
  - Correspondence - Governments, 1974 - 1987; F-149-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 149-3)
    Pending review
  - Correspondence - University administrators, 1969 - 1986; F-149-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 149-3)
  - Correspondence - University President and Board of Governors, 1966 - 1986; F-149-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 149-3)
- Publications, 1969 - 1995; F-149-3; 11 cm of textual records
  Series consists mostly of publications related to childcare at SFU. Also includes two files of general reference material about childcare in other places. Records consist of newsclippings, newsletters, brochures, parent and staff handbooks, and other documents.
  - Childcare General Reference Material, 1969 - 1977; F-149-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 149-4)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-149-3-0-5.
  - Newsclippings About SFU Childcare, 1970 - 1995; F-149-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 149-4)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-149-3-0-3.
  - Daycare Brochures and Publications, 1974 - 1995; F-149-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 149-4)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-149-3-0-1.
  - Daycare News, 1981 - 1983; F-149-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 149-4)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-54-5-1-11.
  - Childcare Newsletter, 1984 - 1985; F-149-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 149-4)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-54-5-1-13.
  - Daycare News, 1984 - 1988; F-149-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 149-4)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-54-5-1-12.
  - SFU Childcare Society Staff Handbook, 1987; F-149-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 149-4)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-149-3-0-2.
  - The Grapevine Express, 1988 - 1992; F-149-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 149-4)
  - Newsclippings About Childcare (general), 1993; F-149-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 149-4)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-149-3-0-4.
- Photographs, [1970] - [1979]; F-149-4; 1 cm of textual records 28 photographs; Physical description: 28 photographs located in F-149-4-0-0-1
  Series consists of 23 black and white photographs of the interior and exterior of the SFU Child Care Centre depicting the building, children, and staff members.
  - Photographs, [ca 1970] - [ca 1979]; F-149-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 149-4)
    Textual records; Photographic materials
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-54-5-1-0-14.
- Audio cassette interviews, 1998 - 1999; F-149-5; 6 sound recordings
  Series consists of a set of six sound recording originally on audio cassette. Four of the recordings are interviews with former Executive Directors and the present Executive Director on the occasion of the thirtieth anniversary of childcare at SFU. The remaining sound recordings are copies of radio interviews by broadcaster Rafe Mair with Sheila Davidson and Social Services Minister Lois Boone about the social services strike in 1999.
  Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized)
  Open. Interviews were originally recorded to audio cassettes, but have been digitized. Access to the interviews will be provided through the digitized copies. Consult the reference archivist for more information about accessing these digital recordings.
  Includes originals and copies on 12 audio cassettes. The interviews have also been digitized.
  - Joyce Branscombe interview, March 1998; F-149-5-0-0-0-1 (Audio cassette OBJ-3279, Audio cassette OBJ-3280)
    Joyce Branscombe, Executive Director 1984-1987, interviewed by Tracy Dyke and Sheila Davidson. Topics include a discussion of her work and accomplishments, changes in childcare, and the 30th anniversary of childcare at SFU.
    Branscombe, Joyce E.; Tracy Dyke; Davidson, Sheila; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: C-149-5-0-1.1, C-149-5-0-1.2, F-149-item1, F-149-item7.
  - Emily Campbell interview, March 1998; F-149-5-0-0-0-2 (Audio cassette OBJ-3281, Audio cassette OBJ-3282)
    Emily Campbell, first Executive Director of Child Care (1974-1984), interviewed by Tracy Dyke and Sheila Davidson. Topics include discussion of her work and accomplishments, changes in child care, and the 30th anniversary of child care at SFU.
    Campbell, Emily A.; Tracy Dyke; Davidson, Sheila; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: C-149-5-0-2.1, C-149-5-0-2.2, F-149-item2, F-149-item8.
  - Penny Coates interview, March 1998; F-149-5-0-0-0-3 (Audio cassette OBJ-3283, Audio cassette OBJ-3284)
    Penny Coates, Executive Director 1987-1991, interviewed by Tracy Dyke and Sheila Davidson. Topics include discussion of her work and accomplishments, changes in child care, and the 30th anniversary of child care at SFU.
    Coates, Penny; Tracy Dyke; Davidson, Sheila; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: C-149-5-0-3.1, C-149-5-0-3.2, F-149-item3, F-149-item9.
  - Sheila Davidson interview, March 1998; F-149-5-0-0-0-4 (Audio cassette OBJ-3285, Audio cassette OBJ-3286)
    Sheila Davidson, Executive Director 1991–, interviewed by Tracy Dyke. Topics include discussion of her work and accomplishments, changes in child care, and the 30th anniversary of child care at SFU.
    Davidson, Sheila; Tracy Dyke; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: C-149-5-0-4.1, C-149-5-0-4.2, F-149-item4, F-149-item10.
  - CKNW The Rafe Mair Show, 19 May 1999; F-149-5-0-0-0-6 (Audio cassette OBJ-3311, Audio cassette OBJ-3312)
    Recording of the Rafe Mair Show broadcast on radio CKNW on Wednesday May 19, 1999. Includes an interview of Sheila Davidson by Rafe Mair re: social service strike.
    Davidson, Sheila; Mair, Rafe; CKNW Radio; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: C-149-5-0-5.1, C-149-5-0-5.2, F-149-item5, F-149-item11.
  - CKNW The Rafe Mair Show, 12 May 1999; F-149-5-0-0-0-5 (Audio cassette OBJ-3309, Audio cassette OBJ-3310)
    Recording of the Rafe Mair Show broadcast on radio CKNW on May 12, 1999. Includes interview of Social Services Minister Lois Boone by Rafe Mair re: social services strike.
    CKNW Radio; Mair, Rafe; Lois Boone; Sound recordings; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: C-149-5-0-6.1, C-149-5-0-6.2, F-149-item6, F-149-item12.